Guide to the Papers of John R. Lamarsh 1943-1981 MC.14
New York University Archives
- Series V: Academic Affiliations
  - General: Lecture Material IV, 1958-1959 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - New York University: General, 1961-1973 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225876 7
  - Applied Science, 1972-1975 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Engineering and Science, School of: General, 1963-1977 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - AGN Reactor: Hazards Summary, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - AGN Reactor: Licensing Application, 1963-1964 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - AGN Reactor: Transfer Application, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - EnrollmentIncome, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - General, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Building, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Establishing Center, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Proposal, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Status Report, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - TRIGA Reactor, 1969-1972 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - TRIGAReactor: Safety Analysis, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225877 5
  - Student Papers, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Ford Foundation Study and NYU, 1975-1976 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center, 1974-1980 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Technology and Public Policy, Center for: General, 1965-1979 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Proposal, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Polytechnic Institute of New York: General, 1973-1977 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - AGN Reactor, 1975-1977 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - AGN Reactor Licensing Application, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - ChineseNuclear Society Visit, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Energy Technology andPolicy Center: General, 1979-1980 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Proposal, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 12)
- Series VI: Professional Associations
  This series contains material relating to Dr. Lamarsh's affiliations with various professional associations, including the American Geographical Society, the American Nuclear Energy Council, the Americannuclear Society, the American Program Bureau, the American Society for EngineeringEducation, The New York Academy of Sciences, The New York State Society of ProfessionalEngineers, the Nuclear Engineering Department Heads Organization, the Scientists' Institute forPublic Information and The Center for Strategic and International Studies. Several of thesefolders only briefly document Dr. Lamarsh's connection with their respective organizations, butthe material dealing with the American Nuclear Society is very extensive. Matters concerning theEducation Division of the American Nuclear Society is appropriately documented to reflect Dr.Lamarsh's involvement in the society in varying capacities.
  - American Geographical Society, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225878 3
  - American Nuclear Energy Council, circa 1970s (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - American Nuclear Society: General, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Arthur Holly Compton Award, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Arthur Holly Compton Award, 1981 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Certificate for Governance, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - EducationDivision: General I, 1973-1978 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - General II, 1979-1981 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Honors, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - American Society for Engineering Education, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Book Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Budget, 1977-1979 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Professional Development, 1976-1979 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225879 1
  - Executive Committee I, 1976-1978 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee II, 1979 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee III, 1980-1981 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Honors and Awards Committee, 1978-1978 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter, 1976-1979 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Program Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Proposed Brochure, 1978-1979 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Proposed Revision of Bylaws, 1974-1980 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Student Activities Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - University/Industry Relations Committee, 1975-1980 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Fellow, 1977-1980 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225880 9
  - International Conference, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Need Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - New York Metropolitan Section, 1978-1979 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - New York Metropolitan Section NuclearAwards, 1970-1981 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Nuclear News, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Policy Statements, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Professional Division, 1978-1979 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Standards Committee, 1971-1974 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - SUNYMaritime College, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - American ProgramBureau: Possibility of Receiving Payment for Lectures, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - American Society for Engineering Education, 1967-1968 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - The New York Academy of Sciences, 1974-1980 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - The New York State Society of Professional Engineers, Inc., 1978 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Nuclear Engineering Department HeadsOrganization (NEDHO), 1979-1981 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Scientists' Institutefor Public Information, 1979-1980 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Strategic andInternational Studies, The Center for, 1979-1980 (Box 21, Folder 17)
- Series VII: Publications
  This series includesthree subseries: Books, Other Publications and Proposed Publications. The subseries "Books"documents Dr. Lamarsh's two major publications: Introduction to Nuclear Reactor Theory(1966)and Introduction to Nuclear Engineering (1975). Aside from such technical matters asobtaining permission to use another's work, this subseries consists of correspondence with thepublishing company, some preliminary research material, comments on the two books andmaterial concerning second editions and translations. The subseries "Other Publications" includescopies of various editorials and articles penned by Dr. Lamarsh at various points during hisillustrious career. "Proposed Publications" consists of material, such as handwritten manuscriptsor typescripts that suggests Dr. Lamarsh's interest in publishing certain works which, for onereason or another, were not realized during his lifetime. The four works are: "The Elements ofNuclear Reactor Theory," "Nuclear Engineering Tables," "People, Power and Pollution: AnIntroduction to the Environmental Aspects of Electric Power Production," and "Radiation: OurUnseen Environment." "People, Power and Pollution" was apparently based on a non creditcourse which Dr. Lamarsh gave at New York University during the 1971-72 academic year.
  - Books: Introductionto Nuclear Engineering: General I, 1967-1973 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225881 7
  - General II, 1974-1979 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, 1970-1979 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company,Project editor, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Canadian Reactors, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Comments, 1975-1976 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Errata, First printing, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Rights and Permissions, 1973-1974, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Second Printing, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Solutions Manual, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Introduction to NuclearReactor Theory: General, 1957-1966 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225882 5
  - Addison-WesleyPublishing Company, 1958-1969 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Addison-WesleyPublishing Company, Manuscript Editor, 1965-1969 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Calculations, 1959, 1965-1967 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Comments I, 1961-1966 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225883 3
  - Comments II, 1967-1980 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Figures, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Review Questions, 1974 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Rights andPermissions, 1964-1965 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Second Edition, 1970-1978 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Translation, Japanese, 1971-1977, 1981 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Translation, Korean, 1975-1977 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Other Publications: General, 1975-1980 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225884 1
  - Are Nuclear Protesters Off Target?, 1977 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Atoms for Survival, 1956-1957 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Cornell Daily Sun Editorial, 1959 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - A Defenseof Civil Disobedience for Nuclear Power and "Nuclear Power--Not Nuclear Weapons", 1977 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Newsday Editorial, 1980 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Nuclear Power in Civil Defense, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Nuclear Power and the Energy Crisis, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Producing Power While Curbing Weapons, 1979 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - The Scope of Nuclear Engineering, 1968 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - The Shelter Plan, 1960 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - Shelters Will Shelter, 1961 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - General, 1979-1980 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Research Materials, 1976-1979 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - What Reactor Failures?, 1979-1980 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Proposed Publications: The Elements of Nuclear Reactor TheoryProposed Second Edition, 1958-1966 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225885 8
  - NuclearEngineering Tables: Proposed book, 1965-1973 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - People, Power and Pollution: An Introduction to the Environmental Aspects of Electric PowerProduction:General, 1970 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 1, 1970 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 2, undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 5, undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Graphs, undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Radiation: Our Unseen Environment:General, 1975-1976 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, 1975-1976 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Outline, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Introduction, undated (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Chapter 1, undated (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Chapter 2, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225886 6
  - Chapter 3, undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 4, undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 5, undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 6, undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
- Series VIII: Speeches
  This series consists of scripts of speeches, which Dr. Lamarsh addressed to various audiences. Thereis also some correspondence, which reflects the responses of some of his audiences.
  - General, 1960-1979 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225887 4
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1960-1961 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - American Nuclear Society, 1979 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution, 1979-1981 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Ethical Culture of Queens, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Harlem School of the Arts: Serious Talks for Busy People, 1976 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Health Physics Society, 1970 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Mamaroneck Public Schools: The Hommocks School, 1977 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Mamaroneck Public Schools: Mamaroneck High School, 1979 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - National Research Council: Hearings, 1976 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - New York Academy of Sciences, 1979-1980 (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - New York Academy of Sciences:Conference on the Three Mile IslandNuclear Accident, 1977-1980 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - New York Academy of Sciences, Junior Academy of, 1979 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - New York University: Nuclear Reactor Building, 1966 (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - North Carolina State University, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - Physics Club of New York, 1979-1980 (Box 28, Folder 16)
  - Polytechnic Institute of New York: Bi-CountyExecutive Breakfast, 1975 (Box 28, Folder 17)
  - Polytechnic Institute ofNew York: Continuing Education Course, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 18)
  - Port Washington Library, 1979 (Box 28, Folder 19)
  - Sarah Lawerence College, 1979 (Box 28, Folder 20)
  - Society of Friends, 1977 (Box 28, Folder 21)
  - University Club of Larchmont, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 22)
- Series IX:Personal
  This series briefly documents Dr. Lamarsh's academic and military career. Contained within the folder are three letters written by Albert Einstein to Lamarsh in 1945 in response to Lamarsh's inquiries regarding a subject he was researching. The originals have been removed to a restricted file.
  - Air Force, 1947-1953 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225888 2
  - Atomic EnergyCommission Predoctoral Fellowship, 1950-1952 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Information, 1959-1980 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Clubs, 1960-1963, 1977-1980 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Edison ElectricInstitute's Power Engineering Educator Award, 1975-1976 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - High School, 1943-1945 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - JobApplications/Opportunities, 1967-1981 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1945-1957, 1972-1977 (Box 29, Folder 8)
- Series X:Photographs, Clippings, and Recordings
  The last series in the collection consists of a few photographs thatwere found dispersed in the collection, several newspaper clippings on subjects in which Dr.Lamarsh apparently had an interest and two taped recordings of a Breeder Technology Seminar,which he conducted in 1981. SUMMARY The Lamarsh Papers contain a great deal of valuableinformation for the researcher. The series Consulting Services provides a wealth of informationabout Dr. Lamarsh's work as a consultant to various agencies and reflects his nuclear energypolicies. It includes studies and reports on research projects which he undertook for governmentand private agencies. The material documenting Dr. Lamarsh's work on advisory committees alsoreflects his attitudes towards several nuclear energy issues. Although the series Research Interestsis not particularly rich, it may suggest the wide variety of subjects in which Lamarsh took aninterest and it may also provide information as to how his research interests evolved during hiscareer. Regardless of his long tenure at New York University and the Polytechnic Institute ofNew York, the material in the series Academic Affiliations is not very extensive. It may,however, give the researcher a perspective of Dr. Lamarsh's involvement as an educator, as theseries on Professional Associations may provide a perspective of his activities in variousprofessional societies. The series on Publications and Speeches may suggest Dr. Lamarsh's senseof obligation to educate people about nuclear energy as well his concern with contemporaryattitudes towards nuclear issues. The Lamarsh Papers offer a rich resource for those interested inthe history of nuclear physics, in general, and in the career and point of view of a worldrenowned physicist in particular.
  - Photographs, 1955-1968 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225889 0
  - News Items I, undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - News Items II, 1959-1981 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Tapes of BreederTechnology Seminar, 1981 (Box 30, Folder 4)
- Series X: Photographs, Clippings, and Recordings Appendix I
  - Speeches: Sarah Lawrence College; The U.S. Energy Crisis; March 2, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_7456fbbdfca0497a73fd632ee1739c59)
  - Cooper Union; Three Mile Island Accident; April 10, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_5a33bd2cab84bafb1559ff8112df8cea)
  - Northeastern New York American Nuclear Society; Nuclear Weapons Proliferation; April 30, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_20c45e28411279e11d5768fad1da2875)
  - New York Community College; Nuclear Power Plant Safety; May 17, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_82569a17c321d3412a42056b5b6dff7f)
  - New York Academy of Sciences;The U.S. Energy Crisis; May 25, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_037789c03cc115311701bd0bbc877d5b)
  - Seoul National University (Korea); Nuclear Power Plant Safety; June 15, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_33a1612dd745858c72a16917ff6a137f)
  - Peking International Center (China); Nuclear Power in the U.S.; June 21, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_f67d2d01a23b86ee23a0d2e102e02d1a)
  - Peking International Center (China); Nuclear Power Plant Safety; June 22, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_121152b38ae70c90677778cac494577e)
  - Xian Jiaotung University (China); Nuclear Engineering Education; June 26, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_59d9dc59bc41b33485a616f2838d6158)
  - Asian Institute of Technology (Bangkok); Nuclear Power in the U.S.; July 2, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_33a8c88d70d8636d188118087739fca6)
  - Nuclear Power in China; August 3, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_72b97cf356e42b377fc01d8e3a9f5fff)
  - Radio Station WPLJ; Nuclear Power Safety; September 20, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_8bde08a30ea7e9acc9cdaacb36aee7e5)
  - Port Washington, New York Lecture Series; The U.S. Energy Crisis; October 23, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_d28c96994259bf245943091f7b1a25a2)
  - Mamaroneck High School; Our Radiation Environment; October 26, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_ff81d22b534825666ee707cb84de97f2)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution: Westchester, New York Chapter; The U.S. Energy Crisis; November 15, 1979 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_726a7664d5a8ed079804ffe5a98d5602)
  - North Carolina State University; Nuclear Weapons Proliferation; January 24, 1980 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_358ad8aeaec101ac525c0922f0ef0f9a)
  - Radio Station WNYC; Science Talk; February 20, 1980 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_e198f30b5cf75911aae944780d459156)
  - The Physics Club of New York; The U.S. Energy Crisis; March 28, 1980 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_8bf203f38f828ab0b7d8e5dffee41bed)
  - University Club of Larchmont; The U.S. Energy Crisis; March 20, 1980 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_071a266dae628bb68c553d2f80e5c2ae)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution: Greenwich, Connecticut Chapter; The U.S. Energy Crisis; March 28, 1980 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_8d96048472fae32992cae2770d1c0b8f)
  - New York Academy of Sciences (Conference); Nuclear Power Plant Safety; April 8, 1980 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_8e104b79ad3842e2b19c61952c047423)
  - Ethical Culture Society of Queens, New York; The U.S. Energy Crisis; April 13, 1980 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_88aac722f2829ba2d1a98b3176a30440)
  - Citizens for Safe Energy, Briefing; The U.S. Energy Crisis; June 17, 1980 (Box 30, Folder data_value_missing_2edcbb53a0ad51c4e22cf4c1ab913b15)